Guide to Voices of Crown Heights oral histories 2016.027
Brooklyn Historical Society
Voices of Crown Heights oral histories
2016-2017
2017
Brooklyn Historical Society
Ali, Zaheer
Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Movement Center (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Johnson, Walis
Kitto, Svetlana
Mondésir, Obden
Okechukwu, Amaka
Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History
2016.027
42 Gigabytes in 119 files; Running time (of described records): 66 hours, 34 minutes, 20 seconds. All recordings and transcripts were born-digital.
This collection includes oral histories conducted by Brooklyn Historical Society (BHS), Brooklyn Movement Center (BMC), and Weeksville Heritage Center (WHC) beginning in 2016 and collected and arranged by BHS in 2017. The assembled collection was part of broader programming efforts by the three organizations to commemorate and examine the transforming Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn a quarter-century after the August 1991 conflicts and unrest sometimes called "the Crown Heights riot." The oral history collection features a broad range of narrators; educators, community organizers, activists, entrepreneurs, artists, bloggers, and longtime neighborhood residents, who describe the changes they have observed in their neighborhood over decades.
Historical note
History of Crown Heights: From the late nineteenth century up to the World War I era, the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights was known for being an upper and upper middle class residential enclave. Russian Jews, Irish, and Italians moved there as a part of the boom in immigration from 1880 to 1940. Smaller migrations to Crown Heights occurred as well, with Caribbean migrants among these. Seeing an opportunity for first-time home ownership, some of Harlem's African American residents moved to the neighborhood in the 1930s. A great wave of Caribbean immigration followed in the 1960s and 1970s. With many White residents removing to the suburbs, those immigrants along with Caribbean Americans and African Americans invested and lived in the majority of residences from the 1960s to the 1990s. The Lubavitcher Hasidim, a Judaic movement that established its headquarters in Crown Heights in 1940, accounted for about eight percent of the population, according to 1990s figures. In 1991, long simmering tensions between members of the Lubavitcher and Black communities, and two fatalities, propelled the neighborhood into three days of unrest and violence. Encapsulated by the news media as the "Crown Heights Riot," the community took years to heal. Another demographic shift began as the 1990s ended; and by 2010 a new confluence of amenities, development, and rising property values was affecting the diverse face of the roughly 130,000 residents.
Voices of Crown Heights project: Staff for this project included Zaheer Ali (Oral Historian), Amaka Okechukwu (Project Coordinator), Svetlana Kitto (Interviewer), Walis Johnson (Interviewer), Obden Mondésir (Interviewer), and several more interviewers. From December 2016 to April 2017, project staff conducted three workshops for community partners and affiliates, with the purpose of informing participants about the neighborhood history, exposing participants to primary sources, and training participants in oral history methods. Unique to the Voices of Crown Heights project was its public engagement with oral history and contemporary neighborhood concerns. A first set of programs were done in partnership with WHC, and the second with BMC; BHS concluded with two final programs in June and July 2017. Project staff have presented about the Voices of Crown Heights at conferences, seminars, and panel discussions, engaging specialists, scholars, and oral history practitioners.
Scope and Contents
The Voices of Crown Heights oral histories feature a range of narrators from diverse backgrounds. Several have been immersed in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn for a relatively brief, recent, and rapidly gentrifying period of the early twenty-first century. Others have first-hand experience with the community for roughly a quarter century prior, and can contrast the earlier period with the later one. This collection focused on recent history and social interaction in Crown Heights, with particular interest being paid to the August 1991 conflict in the neighborhood, public schools, gentrification, and policing and safety.
Arrangement
The collection of oral history interviews is organized into three series based on collaborative community partnerships within the project. Series 1: Brooklyn Historical Society consists of recordings conducted by the in-house Oral Historian and Project Coordinator, as well as by interviewers consulting for the institution.
Series 2: Brooklyn Movement Center includes interviewers linked to the project through their participation with the Brooklyn Movement Center, including the organization's Project Coordinator and consultants.
Oral histories represented in Series 3: Weeksville Heritage Center contain interviews conducted by that institution's Oral History Project Manager and the institution's consultants.
Conditions Governing Access
Oral histories can be accessed onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online at the Oral History Portal.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The oral histories that make up this collection were conducted by staff or consultants for Brooklyn Historical Society, Brooklyn Movement Center, or Weeksville Heritage Center. Preparation took place in 2016 and the bulk of the oral histories were created in 2017.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Historical Society has oral history collections and other records related to the Voices of Crown Heights oral histories.
• The Crown Heights History Project collection includes thirty-three interviews conducted from 1993 to 1994 (1994.006)
• The West Indian Carnival Documentation Project Records includes thirty-four interviews dating from 1994 to 1995 (2010.019)
• The Listen to this: Crown Heights Oral History collection includes forty-three interviews conducted in 2010 (2010.020). Narrators Karim, Camara, Richard Green, Constance Lesold, Evangeline Porter, and Meredith Staton were also recorded for this collection.
• 959 Park Place Tenants' Association records (1978.009)
• Eastern Parkway Coalition records, 1952-2007 (2007.016)
• Mark Naison papers, 1931-2011 (2016.021)
Collections related to the community activism referenced in these oral histories include:
• Arnie Goldwag Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) collection (ARC.002)
• Bob Adelman photographs of Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) demonstrations (V1989.022)
Oral History note
Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between two people, both of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Brooklyn Historical Society archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that:
1. The Brooklyn Historical Society abides by the General Principles & Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics.
2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access whenever possible, BHS presents these views as recorded.
3. Transcripts commissioned by a party other than BHS serve as a guide to the interview and are not considered verbatim. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, repetitions that are common in conversation, and other passages and phrases omitted from the transcript. This decision was made because BHS gives primacy to the audible voice and also because some researchers do find useful information in these verbal patterns.
4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator's speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
Bibliography
Goldschmidt, Henry. Race and Religion Among the Chosen Peoples of Crown Heights New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University Press, 2006.
Gregor, Alison. "Crown Heights, Brooklyn, Where Stoop Life Still Thrives." New York Times. (New York, NY), June 17, 2015.
Shapiro, Edward S. Crown Heights: Blacks, Jews, and the 1991 Brooklyn Riot Waltham, MA: Brandeis University Press, 2006.
Interviews (sound recordings); Oral histories (document genres); Transcripts; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhood government |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Congress of Racial Equality; New York (N.Y.). Police Department
- Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Brooklyn Historical Society, 2016-2017; 2016.027.1
  - Bembry-Guet, Dorothy, 2017 May 17; 2016.027.1.11
    Biographical note
    Born in 1942 in Georgia, Dorothy Bembry-Guet moved to New York City in 1968. The Prospect Heights and Crown Heights neighborhoods of Brooklyn have largely been her places of residence, the latter for twenty-five years as of 2017. She married in 1974 and had one child. Bembry-Guet worked primarily for the New York University (NYU) Medical Center. She received a bachelor's degree in communications and political science from NYU in 1992. Bembry-Guet has devoted much of her life to activism; including work with the Brooklyn Tenants Union, Legal Hand, Crown Heights Mediation Center, two terms as chair of the political action committee in the Service Employees International Union (SEIU) 1199 local, and as a member of the public safety and park committees of Community Board Eight in Crown Heights. Retired, with limited mobility, at the time of the 2017 interview, Bembry-Guet had also pursued healthcare reform as a lobbyist in Albany.
    Scope and Contents
    In the interview, Dorothy Bembry-Guet recalls her early experiences with moving and adjusting to New York City, and looking for housing in Brooklyn. She describes the neighborhoods of Prospect Heights and Crown Heights, their amenities and cultural landmarks, and their gentrification over decades. Throughout, Bembry-Guet refers to her varied and evolving efforts at activism, including tenants' rights, public safety and healthcare. She remembers local community leader Arthur Miller and protests over his death at the hands of the New York Police Department. Pointing out her participation in local community organizations, she talks about the work of the Mediation Center and their Save Our Streets (SOS) initiative. Interview conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    Conditions Governing Access and Use
    Access to the interview is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal. Use of the oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires permission from BHS by contacting library@brooklynhistory.org.
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police brutality |z United States; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Politicians |z New York (State); Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Bembry-Guet, Dorothy; Community Board No. 8 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights Mediation Center; Lesold, Constance; Miller, Arthur, Jr.; Muse Community Museum (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Police Department; NYU Langone Medical Center
  - Camara, Karim, 2017 May 18; 2016.027.1.12
    Born Karim Abdur-Razzaq in Brooklyn, New York, in 1971, Karim Camara spent most of childhood and young adult life in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. His father Abdullah Abdur-Razzaq was an activist who had served as a chief aide to Malcolm X, and his mother Ora Clark Razzaq was an educator who co-founded and served as principal of Al-Karim School, an independent school in Crown Heights. The school evolved into the Cush Campus School and was in operation for 45 years. Camara attended the school up to fifth grade, and went on to attend Brooklyn Friends School from grades eight through twelve. After college he went on to attend New York Theological Seminary, and he served the congregants of the First Baptist Church of Crown Heights, first as associate and then executive pastor. In 2005, he was elected to the New York State Assembly, where he served until 2015, when he became the Executive Director of the Governor's Office of Faith-Based Community Development. He is an ordained minister, and founding and senior pastor of Abundant Life Church in Brooklyn.
    In this interview, Karim Camara talks about growing up in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, and his political and spiritual journeys to government service and church leadership respectively. He describes the disciplined but also nurturing and loving environment of the independent school that his parents founded. He recalls the time he spent helping his mother with the school, and the stories his father told him about working with Malcolm X. He talks about his and his family's interactions with their Jewish and West Indian neighbors, and he fondly recalls childhood games at Brower Park. He recounts his spiritual evolution, including his decision to attend seminary, his pastoral leadership at First Baptist Church of Crown Heights, and his name change. He relates how his experiences at First Baptist inspired him to enter electoral politics, and eventually work with faith based communities on behalf of New York State. Finally, he reflects on the changes in Crown Heights over the years, and the impact of gentrification. Karim Camara was also recorded for the Listen to this: Crown Heights Oral History collection in 2010 (2010.020). His mother, Ora Clark Razzaq, was also recorded for Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Brooklyn Historical Society. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
    African Americans -- Politics and government -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Christian life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Municipal government |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Pan-Africanism; Private schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race identity; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Al-Karim School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Friends School; Camara, Karim; Clark Razzaq, Ora; Cush Campus Schools (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); First Baptist Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Griffith, Michael, 1963-1986; Miller, Arthur, Jr.; New York (State). Legislature. Assembly; Norman, Clarence, Jr.; Uhuru Sasa School; Weusi, Jitu, 1939-2013; X, Malcolm, 1925-1965
  - Clark, Ora, 2017 June 2; 2016.027.1.16
    Ora Clark Razzaq, seventy-nine years of age at the time of the interview, is an African American woman. She began the Al-Karim School, later renamed Cush Campus Schools, in the 1970s as a way to educate her children. Informed by her participation in supporting the community schools in the Ocean Hill-Brownsville neighborhoods of Brooklyn in the wake of the teacher's strike of 1968, she began her Black independent school as an alternative to the public school system which she saw as failing Black children. She was formerly married to Abdullah Abdur-Razzaq (approximately mid 1960s to late 1970s), one of Malcolm X's close associates.
    In this interview, Ora Clark (also known as Ora Clark Razzaq) recounts moving to New York City as a child from Miami, Florida. Her family lived in the Lower East Side/Greenwich Village neighborhoods of Manhattan, which was predominantly Jewish at the time. The family eventually moved to the St. Albans neighborhood of Queens. She speaks about moving to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn as a young mother and being involved in actions in response to the teacher's strike in the nearby Ocean Hill-Brownsville neighborhood. She began Al-Karim School soon after, which was later renamed Cush Campus Schools once it began educating a larger amount of students. She first began teaching her children, then the children of others in the community. Clark speaks about the different approach that the school had from others, in valuing the children and taking them outside the classroom; students traveled abroad to places in Europe and Guyana. Throughout the interview, she speaks about neighbors who looked down on her and Al-Karim School; which began in her home on Park Place in Crown Heights, and later functioned out of 221 Kingston Avenue, the Historic First Church of God in Christ. She also speaks about organizer Arthur Miller, the 1977 blackout, and gentrification. Her son, Karim Camara, was also recorded for Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Brooklyn Historical Society. Interview conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    Activism; African Americans |x Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Electric power failures |z New York (State) |z New York; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.); Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Private schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Al-Karim School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Clark Razzaq, Ora; Cush Campus Schools (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); East Educational and Cultural Center for People of African Descent (1969-1986) (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Miller, Arthur, Jr.; Uhuru Sasa School; Weusi, Jitu, 1939-2013
  - Cohen, Eli, 2017 May 26; 2016.027.1.14
    Rabbi Eli Cohen was born in Manchester, England in 1955. He moved to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1973 to study Lubavitch Hasidim in Morristown, New Jersey. He organized Mitzvah tanks, the roaming vehicles promoting and teaching the orthodox religion, in the mid-1970s. The rabbi became director of Chabad at New York University in 1985 before becoming Executive Director of Crown Heights Jewish Community Council in 2003.
    In this interview, Rabbi Cohen talks about moving to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn at the onset of the Yom Kippur War of 1973, and the sense of celebration that existed in Crown Heights throughout the war. He describes relationships between the New York Police Department and the Hasidic community at different points over his forty year history in the neighborhood and reflects on crime in Crown Heights, and the relationship between Jewish and Black communities within that context. He briefly reflects on the blackout of 1977, the summer of 1991, crime, and Kingston Avenue's appearance over decades. He describes the Hasidic community as politically involved and narrates the emergence of Community Board Nine in South Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Matthew Birkhold.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Electric power failures |z New York (State) |z New York; Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Cohen, Eli, Rabbi; Community Board No. 9 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Cuthbert, Donna, 2017 August 25; 2016.027.1.23
    Born in 1956, Donna Cuthbert was raised in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Her family was originally from Barbados, and she is second generation American. She went to schools in Crown Heights and the Prospect Lefferts Gardens and Flatbush neighborhoods of Brooklyn-- including an unusual educational experience in the alternative school, Wingate Prep-- and went to college to become a teacher in New Rochelle, New York. Following in her father's footsteps, she became a bartender of a Crown Heights bar, the Starlite Lounge. The Starlite was one of the oldest city bars to welcome gay, as well as heterosexual, patrons. Between 2004 and 2010, Cuthbert-- known to some as "Mama Donna"-- then worked the door of the Starlite, until the building was sold and the bar was permanently closed. She is married and continues to reside in Crown Heights as of 2017.
    In this interview, Donna Cuthbert talks about growing up in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in the fifties and sixties. Her father was the manager at the Unity Bar and Grill, and she describes characters and scenes from the place. Her mother was a registered nurse at Brooklyn Hospital, and Cuthbert cites the extreme racism her mother experienced there. She mentions the politics in her household and the political meetings she attended as an adolescent. Additionally she recalls her time at Wingate Prep, a satellite of Brooklyn's Wingate High that, along with a few other schools, sought to restructure secondary education in 1970s New York City. Cuthbert remembers sneaking into the Starlite Lounge when she a young teen. She relates how she started work at the Starlite much later as an adult. She describes the different nights at the bar, and the range of clientele it attracted. She gives an overview and shares specifics on the array of characters who frequented the Starlite. She also talks about personal relationships she made with customers. She describes losing William "Butchie" King, the disc jockey who ran the Starlite for years. Finally, Cuthbert reflects on the bar's closing; how it happened, how the nightlife there had changed, the final hours, the fallout for patrons and the community, and the signaling of greater gentrification. Interview conducted by Svetlana Kitto.